<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbookV4.5/docbookx.dtd" []>
<article>
  <title>
    <inlinegraphic fileref="img/bliskenya.png" width="150" align="center"/>
  </title>
  <articleinfo>
    <releaseinfo>
      <emphasis role="bold">User Guide</emphasis>
    </releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo>BLIS-Kenya v2.5 - A joint initiative of C4G @ Georgia Tech, the CDC, </releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo>@iLabAfrica - Strathmore University , Association of Public Health Laboratories (APHL) and participating countries</releaseinfo>
  </articleinfo>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <para/>
  <section>
    <title>What is BLIS? </title>
    <para>The Basic Laboratory Information System, BLIS, is a freeware Web-based system that 
can be installed in a local, district, or national laboratory. It is a tool that can help to 
standardize data, which improves the ability to run useful reports and can both give a 
realistic picture of laboratory services and assist with staff and budget planning. With 
enough data, BLIS can be used to track disease prevalence over time</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <para>Features of BLIS include: </para>
      <listitem>
        <para>One-time entry of each unique patient</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Standardization of data collected (allowable entries for specimen type, test type, 
patient data, reagents are set at MOH level and then entered consistently 
throughout a country)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Customization to a country’s needs</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ability to track lab supplies such as test kits, reagents</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ability to run reports as specified by a country
• </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Automatic alerting of data values that may be out of range(reference ranges and 
panic values are set at the regional or national level)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Daily logs to be reviewed for data verification</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Simple data backup</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <para>As with any properly implemented electronic record system, BLIS may be found over 
time to improve data accuracy and reduce costs in laboratories. Benefits already seen in 
labs using BLIS:</para>
      <listitem>
        <para>Reduced burden for technicians, as results are available soon after testing</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Improved consistency of data entry</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ability to view patient history and track samples</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ability to aggregate data and analyze data patterns and trends at a regional or 
national level</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Printed patient records in place of handwritten records</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Printed daily logs that make the reports look like the paper forms used in the 
laboratory</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Starting BLIS</title>
    <para>To start the Basic Laboratory Information System, you must click on the bookmark saved on the web browser e.g. Google Chrome or Mozilla Firefox.  You will then see a page requesting login information. You must then enter your credentials to proceed.</para>
    <graphic fileref="img/Untitled.png" align="center"/>
    <para>If you have forgotten your password, kindly contact the lab-in-charge for help</para>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
    <para/>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Manager (Admin) Overview</title>
    <para>The manager interface gives you the ability to add, edit, and delete users as well as 
change laboratory configuration settings. As a manager, you can also generate and print 
reports.
When you log in as an administrator, you see the Manager home page.</para>
    <graphic fileref="img/m_home.png" width="450" align="center"/>
    <para>To switch to technician view, click the <emphasis role="bold">Work as Technician</emphasis> link at the top right of the 
page. To go back to the manager view, click the <emphasis role="bold">Work as Manager</emphasis> link that will be in 
the same place on the screen.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Lab Configuration </title>
    <para>To switch to technician view, click the Work as Technician link at the top right of the 
page. To go back to the manager view, click the Work as Manager link that will be in 
the same place on the screen.</para>
    <para>The various pages of this section are explained in the following pages:</para>
    <section>
      <title>Summary</title>
      <para>This page displays information about lab, specimen types, and test types. It also lists 
technicians’ logins and privileges. </para>
      <graphic fileref="img/lc_summary.png" width="450" align="center"/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Tests</title>
      <section>
        <title>Specimen/TestTypes</title>
        <para>Allows you to set the specimen and test types as appropriate for your country. Click <emphasis role="bold"> Show</emphasis> to reveal and <emphasis role="bold">Hide</emphasis> to close the list. Check the box for each specimen type collected 
or test done at this facility, and click <emphasis role="bold">Submit</emphasis> to save.  </para>
        <graphic fileref="img/lc_testtype.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Target TAT</title>
        <para>Displays turnaround times for tests. To enter or change turnaround time, click <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis>. The 
number and unit (such as “24 hours”) change to a text field and a drop-down list. Enter 
the desired number and choose <emphasis role="bold">Hours</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">Days</emphasis>. When finished, click the <emphasis role="bold">Submit</emphasis> button 
to save changes, or <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> to discard changes. These options are below the list. </para>
        <graphic fileref="img/lc_TAT.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Results Interpretation</title>
        <para>Allows you to specify the interpretation for multiple ranges of values for each test type. 
To view or edit an existing test’s result, choose the test type from the drop-down list and 
click the <emphasis role="bold">Search</emphasis> button. The current interpretation appears. Edit using the text boxes.  </para>
        <para> Click the <emphasis role="bold">Submit</emphasis> button to save changes, <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> to discard them. </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Search</title>
      <para>This section allows you to configure what results are displayed for each patient when a
search is executed. It also allows you to change how many results are displayed on each
page.</para>
      <graphic fileref="img/lc_search.png" width="450" align="center"/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Reports</title>
      <section>
        <title>Infection Report</title>
        <para>Generates an aggregate report of laboratory test results for a particular period for one or 
all lab sections. The tests listed in the report are the ones checked to include on the 
Specimen/Test Types page. Click <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis> to make changes to the details reported. When 
finished, click <emphasis role="bold">Submit</emphasis> button to save changes, <emphasis role="bold">Preview</emphasis> to view the report, <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> to 
discard changes. </para>
        <graphic fileref="img/lc_infection_report.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Test/Specimen Count Reports</title>
        <para>Allows you to set the test and specimen count report content and layout.
click <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis> to make changes. When finished, click the<emphasis role="bold"> Submit </emphasis>button to save changes, or <emphasis role="bold">Cancel </emphasis>to discard changes. </para>
        <graphic fileref="img/lc_testspecimen_report.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Daily Report Settings</title>
        <para>Allows you to set the layout of the Patient Report, Daily Log of Specimens, and Daily 
Log of Patients. Use the drop-down to select the report type, and click<emphasis role="bold"> Search</emphasis>. Edit 
report settings, and add or change a logo to appear on the report. Check or un-check 
boxes to show or hide patient, specimen, and test information. When finished, click the <emphasis role="bold"> Submit</emphasis> button to save changes, or <emphasis role="bold">Cancel </emphasis>to discard changes. These options are below 
the list. </para>
        <graphic fileref="img/lc_daily_report_settings.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Worksheet</title>
        <para>Allows you to create templates to gather patient data in the lab. In lab settings where 
data are not entered at the point of service, the data entry staff enter patient information 
and the tests ordered, then print the worksheet so that lab technicians can write test results 
and other data to be entered into BLIS. Select the <emphasis role="bold">Lab Section</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Test Type</emphasis> and click <emphasis role="bold"> Search</emphasis> to edit the report format. To edit a custom report, click <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis> to the right of the 
report.  To create a new custom worksheet, click the <emphasis role="bold">Add Custom Worksheet</emphasis> link at the 
bottom of the list.</para>
        <graphic fileref="img/lc_worksheet.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Barcode Settings</title>
      <para>To alter the encoding format, barcode width, barcode height and text size.
Click <emphasis role="bold">Barcode Settings</emphasis> on the left menu to make changes and <emphasis role="bold">Submit</emphasis> to save
</para>
      <graphic fileref="img/lc_barcode.png" width="450" align="center"/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>User Accounts</title>
      <para>This page shows all the users with access to the system. It allows you to create new user 
accounts, edit account settings, delete accounts, and monitor account activity.</para>
      <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Add New Account </emphasis>to enter a new user.</para>
      <graphic fileref="img/lc_user1.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      <graphic fileref="img/lc_user2.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Recent Activity</emphasis> opens a new browser page to show the user’s activity by location, 
specimen entry, and results. To view activity by date, enter or edit the start and end dates 
of the range you wish to see and click <emphasis role="bold">View</emphasis>. When you are finished, click <emphasis role="bold">Print</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">Close This Page</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>Click<emphasis role="bold"> Edit</emphasis> for a user to edit user account details or to reset password. <emphasis role="bold">User Type</emphasis> dictates 
the access the user has in the system.<emphasis role="bold"> Reset Password</emphasis> allows you as administrator to 
enter a new password for this user. Click <emphasis role="bold">Submit</emphasis> button to save changes, <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> to 
discard.</para>
      <para>To remove a user account, click the <emphasis role="bold">Delete</emphasis> link for that user. A confirmation box appears. 
Click <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> to complete the deletion,<emphasis role="bold"> Cancel</emphasis> to keep that user’s information.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Registration Fields</title>
      <para>This page shows the configuration of the patient registration page. It allows you to create 
mandatory fields and hide the fields that are not used, per your country’s protocols. It
also allows for creation of certain custom fields for Patient registration and new 
Specimen addition which may be needed by certain labs only.
To customize fields, click <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis> to make changes: check the box to display a field, uncheck to hide. Set fields as required. After editing, click <emphasis role="bold">Update</emphasis> button below the fields 
to save changes, <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> to discard. 
To create new fields, choose the <emphasis role="bold">Add New</emphasis> link for which to add, and enter field name 
and type. Click <emphasis role="bold">Submit</emphasis> button to save changes, <emphasis role="bold">Cancel </emphasis>to discard. </para>
      <graphic fileref="img/lc_registration.png" width="450" align="center"/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Export Configuration</title>
      <para>Use this feature to export all configuration settings to Microsoft Word. Clicking this link 
opens a new browser tab with a preview showing all preset and custom fields as well as 
report settings. The preview has three buttons at the top: Print, Export as Word document, 
and Close. 
Click the <emphasis role="bold">Print</emphasis> button to open the print dialog box; Export as Word document to create 
a file named <emphasis role="bold">blisreport_[date of report].doc</emphasis>, which you may open or save, or <emphasis role="bold">Close</emphasis> to 
close this browser tab.  </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Test Catalog </title>
    <section>
      <title>Lab Sections</title>
      <para>This provides the  option to add a new section. Click Add New to add a new section, Submit to save and Cancel to discard. On the right of the section list click <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis> to make changes and <emphasis role="bold">Delete</emphasis>  to remove the section   </para>
      <graphic fileref="img/tc_labsections.png" width="450" align="center"/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Test Types</title>
      <para>This is the place to add or edit test types used in your laboratory.  
Click <emphasis role="bold">Add New</emphasis> to enter a new test type. Required fields are <emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>, which is a text box;<emphasis role="bold">Lab Section</emphasis>, a drop-down list that includes an option to add a new section; <emphasis role="bold"> Measures</emphasis>, 
which are editable; and <emphasis role="bold">Compatible Specimens</emphasis>, which allows you to check one or more 
specimens that can be used for this test. 
Optional fields include <emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis> (text box), <emphasis role="bold">Clinical Data</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Panel Test</emphasis> (a check-box, 
checked for Yes), <emphasis role="bold">Hide Patient’s Name in report</emphasis> (drop-down Yes/No), <emphasis role="bold">Prevalence Threshold</emphasis> 
(text box), and <emphasis role="bold">Target TAT</emphasis> (text box).
To edit the information about a test type, find the one you wish to edit on the list and then 
click the <emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis> link in the far-right column. 
Click <emphasis role="bold">Submit </emphasis>button to save changes, <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> to discard. </para>
      <graphic fileref="img/tc_testtypes.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      <graphic fileref="img/tc_testtnew.png" width="450" align="center"/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Specimen Types</title>
      <para>This is the place to add or edit specimen types used in your laboratory. 
Click Add New to enter a new specimen type. Required fields are Name, which is a text 
box for entering the name of the specimen, and Compatible Tests, which allows you to 
check the tests that can be performed using that specimen. Ctrl-F opens the Find function 
to search for a test. You may enter a Description of the specimen type, which is optional.
To edit the information about a specimen type, find the one you wish to edit on the list 
and then click the Edit link in the far-right column. 
Click Submit button to save changes, Cancel to discard. </para>
      <graphic fileref="img/tc_specimentyps.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      <graphic fileref="img/tc_specimentypnw.png" width="450" align="center"/>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Technician Overview</title>
    <para>When you log in as a technician, you see this home page:</para>
    <graphic fileref="img/New Picture (1).png" width="450" align="center"/>
    <para>Users with Technician rights can edit your profile to add or change email, phone, and profile picture. Username cannot be changed.
Hover on the top right side of the top bar where you see your username e.g. Wasike.
Click on the username to open a dropdown menu with ‘Edit profile’ and ‘Logout’ items as shown.
</para>
    <graphic fileref="img/New Picture (21).png" width="450" align="center"/>
    <para>Once you click on ‘Edit profile’, you’ll get the following form</para>
    <graphic fileref="img/New Picture.png" width="450" align="center"/>
    <para>Update your details as appropriate and click on the ‘Update’ button
To change your password, use the ‘Change password’ link on the ‘Edit profile’ form as shown.
</para>
    <graphic fileref="img/New Picture (2).png" width="450" align="center"/>
    <para>Fill in the form carefully and save the changes using the ‘Update’ button.
Do not share your password with anyone else and please do not forget your password.
</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title> Reports</title>
    <para>Any user (Technician or Manager) can generate reports.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Daily Reports</title>
      <para>The Patient Report and Daily Log should be run every day. </para>
      <section>
        <title>Patient Report</title>
        <para>Search for the patient by Patient Name, Patient Number, or Patient ID. Click the Search 
button to start search. Select the patient you want from the list if more than one patient 
matches your search criteria. Click <emphasis role="bold">View Report</emphasis> to see all data for that patient, or Select <emphasis role="bold"> Tests</emphasis> to see tests ordered and the results for that patient. 
You can edit the report to show activity within a date range, include pending tests for 
which results are not available, set printing information, or export to Word using the 
controls at the top of the page. </para>
        <graphic fileref="img/r_home.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Daily Log</title>
        <para>Set the date range to reflect the log to print. You can run a report of the day’s activity by 
patients seen (by clicking <emphasis role="bold">Patient Records</emphasis>), or by tests run (by clicking <emphasis role="bold">Test Records</emphasis>). 
If you choose Test Records, You can choose to run a log for one lab section or for one 
type of test. The default settings are test records, all sections, and all tests. The report 
opens in a new browser tab and has <emphasis role="bold">Print</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Export</emphasis> controls at the top of the page.</para>
        <graphic fileref="img/r_dlpatient_records.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Aggregate Reports</title>
      <section>
        <title>Prevalence Rate</title>
        <para>Gives the prevalence of a particular laboratory test result based on the number of tests 
done and the results. Set a date range to view infection graph and prevalence rates. Click <emphasis role="bold"> Submit </emphasis>to run the report, which will open in a new browser tab. 
You can also view the trends of the laboratory test results for the defined period, as a 
graph, by clicking the <emphasis role="bold">Trends</emphasis> option after the report is displayed.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Counts</title>
        <para>Generates a report for a particular time period of the number of tests, specimens, or 
doctor statistics. Set a date range and choose <emphasis role="bold">Test Count</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Specimen Count</emphasis>, or <emphasis role="bold">Doctor</emphasis> 
Statistics to run the desired report.</para>
        <graphic fileref="img/r_testcount_u.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title> Turnaround Time</title>
        <para>Allows you to see actual turnaround times between test order and completion for all or 
specific tests. Set a date range and choose whether to include <emphasis role="bold">Impending Tests</emphasis>. The 
default is completed tests only. It also generates a 
graph of the statistics.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Infection Report</title>
        <para>Allows you to generate reports of infections by patient age and gender. Set a date range and select one <emphasis role="bold">Lab Section</emphasis>, or all sections to see all test results. The report opens in a new browser tab. It also provides an option to create a Word document of the generated report.</para>
        <graphic fileref="img/r_infectionreport.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title> User Statistics</title>
        <para>Provides user report for a particular time period. For Collective User Statistics Click <emphasis role="bold">Collective User Stats</emphasis> then use check boxes; <emphasis role="bold">Patients Registered</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Specimens Registered</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Tests Registered </emphasis>and <emphasis role="bold">Results Entered</emphasis> to determine the report content. And for Individual User Logs Click <emphasis role="bold">Individual User Logs</emphasis> and use the check boxes to determine the report content. Submit to get a report</para>
        <graphic fileref="img/r_userstats.png" width="450" align="center"/>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Appendix</title>
    <section>
      <title>Glossary</title>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Admin</emphasis> – Designation for a user that has control over lab configuration settings </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Aggregate</emphasis> – Type of report that collects data over a period of time and presents it to the user </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Barcodes</emphasis> – Used in inventory management to create printable &apos;barcode&apos; labels for reagents </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Director</emphasis> – Designation for a user that oversees many laboratories, typically at the country level. Manages lab configuration standardization </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Grouped Reports</emphasis> – Reports that cover multiple types of information. </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Inventory</emphasis> – Interface for managing reagents and supplies </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Lab Configuration</emphasis> – Collection of customizable settings relating to the collection and storage of data </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Manager</emphasis> – Another name for an Admin user </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Patient</emphasis> – Entry for a patient whose specimens tests are performed on </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Prevalence Rate</emphasis> – The percentage rate of occurrence of a particular result of tests </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Reagent</emphasis> – Term used in inventory control in BLIS. Denotes any physical supply that requires tracking in the inventory system </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Registration</emphasis> – The act of entering a patient into the BLIS program. Creates a unique patient entry that can be associated with specimens and tests </para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold"> Reports</emphasis> – Pages that collect metrics for various types of data. The scope of these reports varies from individual patients to entire groups of laboratories </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Results </emphasis>- The recorded outcome of tests performed on specimens </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Specimen</emphasis> – An entry representing a physical specimen or reading taken from a patient. </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Specimen Type</emphasis> – Classification for different types of specimens </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Technician</emphasis> – A designation for a user who is tasked with entering data into BLIS </para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold"> Test </emphasis>– An entry representing a test or reading taken from a specimen </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Test Type </emphasis>– Classification for different types of tests. </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Turnaround Time</emphasis> – A measurement of the time it takes to receive a result, once a specimen is collected. </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">User</emphasis> – Any person or entity that logs into the BLIS program </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Verify</emphasis> – An action performed on test entries that validates the results for further use </para>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold">Worksheet </emphasis>– Customizable, printable sheets for improving the speed at which information is recorded in a physical sense (i.e. not entered directly into the BLIS program.) </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
